Joseph Risi

Permanent Address: 224 North 5th Street, Apt. 1, Brooklyn, NY 11211 617-835-5275 · jrisi256@gmail.com · https://github.com/jrisi256

Objective:

My skills and experience enable me to build tools designed to collect and interpret both quantitative and qualitative data which can then be used to help communities/organizations make better decisions. I want to use my skills and experience in a community/organization committed towards social progress.

Education:

Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, NJ

2015

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science, High Honors GPA: 3.889

Bachelor of Arts in Philosophy, High Honors

Honors:

Stevens College of Arts and Letters Creative Writing Award in 2014, Dean's List 2012-2015, Julia and Frederick Bissinger Award from the College of Arts and Letters in 2015, Stevens Department of Computer Science Senior Design Award in 2015, Successfully Hiked the Appalachian Trail in 2015.

Skills:

Programming Experience: C, C++, Java, Python, R, Bash

Software: Docker, Github, Amazon Web Services, Jupyter, RStudio, Microsoft Office Suite

Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQL Server

Languages: Fluent in English, conversational Spanish

Work Experience

MDRC, Manhattan, NY

November 2017 - Current

Data Scientist

- Manage MDRC's cloud-based experimental lab entitled the "DataLab". Managing involves communicating with users about their needs and wants, keeping software up-to-date, and conducting educational sessions with researchers about new data analysis techniques as well as new software.
- Conduct educational sessions on a variety of topics including but not limited to: the tidyverse in R for data cleaning and analysis, using the sf and related packages for geospatial analysis in R, creating a language analysis pipeline starting with web scraping using BeautifulSoup + lxml in Python and ending with topic modelling and finding word embeddings.
- Assisting a research project conducting a causal investigation of the Supervised Release alternative
 to bail program in NYC. Assistance involves running a multivariate regression model in a regression
 discontinuity design context, finding associated statistical significance, checking for robustness, and
 visualizing results.
- Serve as an alternate on our company's IRB (institutional review board) which is tasked with ensuring all research complies with federal ethical guidelines.

Microsoft Research, Manhattan, NY

December 2015 - June 2017

Graduation Date: May

Research Assistant

- Aided senior researchers in the design and administering of experiments and in the analysis of data obtained experimentally or otherwise.
- Designed a survey to learn about peoples' interactions within their social networks through the use of SurveyGizmo, ran a pilot version on Amazon's Mechanical Turk, launched the full version on YouGov, and conducted subsequent analysis in R using mostly multivariate regression.
- Worked on developing a machine learning model to predict classification categories for the documents comprising the History Lab database as well as using topic modeling to gain a better understanding of the contents of the documents.

Center for Decision Technologies, Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, NJ

Research Assistant

May 2012 – June 2014

- Developed data collectors using the BeautifulSoup Python library, Selenium, and Thingiverse API.
- Managed several MySQL databases to store data from several online communities including Twitter, Wikipedia, Github, Thingiverse, and Kickstarter.
- Built tools in Python using numpy and Amazon Web Services to analyze data obtained from these open online communities.

Volunteer Experience:

Court Watch NYC, Brooklyn, NY

Court Watcher

February 2019 - Present

- For 6 12 hours a month, sit in on courtroom arraignment hearings and collected detailed qualitative and quantitative data about the hearings.
- Purpose of data collection is to serve as an accountability mechanism for district attorneys in New

York City. Data collected in courtroom is made public to serve as an accountability/transparency mechanism.

Manny Cantor Community Center, Manhattan, NY

College Mentor

September 2016-February 2017

- Worked for several hours a week with a student to help them complete their college applications.
- Helped student decide upon which colleges to apply to and how to decide which colleges to apply to.
- Helped student write essays and craft answers to short response questions.
- More generally provided emotional support for student and reassured student they would get into a school which was a good fit.

Mongolian National Education and Youth Exchange, Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia

Volunteer English Teacher

July-August 2014

- Taught English as a second language to high school students.
- Provided education about U.S. culture and geography and assisted in the preparation of obtaining a U.S. visa.
- Prepared students for the taking of the TOEFL exam by conducting one on one sessions, doing
 practice examples together, and helping students in identifying and strengthening areas they were
 weak in.

Publications:

 Joseph Risi, Amit Sharma, Rohan Shah, Matthew Connelly, and Duncan J. Watts. "Predicting History." Nature Human Behavior (2019). For access: https://rdcu.be/bFvwT

Acknowledgements:

- Skemer, Melanie, Cindy Redcross, and Jessi LaChance. Forthcoming. Implementation and Impacts of the New York City Pretrial Supervised Release Program. New York: MDRC.
- Andrew Mao, Lili Dworkin, Siddharth Suri, and Duncan J. Watts. "Resilient Cooperators Stabilize Long-Run Cooperation in the Finitely Repeated Prisoner's Dilemma." *Nature Communications* (2017). For access: https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms13800
- Harris Kyriakou, Jeffrey V. Nickerson, and Gaurav Sabnis. "Knowledge Reuse for Customization in an Open Design Community for 3D Printing." *MIS Quarterly* (2017). For access: https://arxiv.org/abs/1702.08072
- Andrew Mao, Winter Mason, Siddharth Suri, and Duncan J. Watts. "An Experimental Study of Team Size and Performance on a Complex Task." PLOS ONE (2016). For access: https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0153048
- Harris Kyriakou. "Collective Innovation: Novelty, Reuse, and Their Interplay." Stevens Institute of Technology (2016). For access: https://ssrn.com/abstract=2931473